Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף Daf is דף י״ט Daf
Yud-Tet and we are picking up in the middle of a discussion
of
סתם נדרים להחמיר ופירושן להקל Stam Nedarim L'hachmir Peyrushan L'hakel that a
language of a נדר Neder that could be interpreted in one way
that even if in both ways the guy was trying to make
a נדר Neder which it seems like he was or she was
but one of them is דבר הנדור Davar Hanadur and the other
is not a דבר הנדור Davar Hanadur so it matters what the
word means and at least the משנה Mishna seemed to give cases
where it was fifty-fifty how to interpret the word and dealt with
cases where one is a more likely explanation than another. It says
we will adopt the more strict interpretation סתם להחמיר Stam L'hachmir
but presumably פירושן להקל Peyrushan L'hakel if the person were to say
no I meant this one rather than that one we would actually
believe the person. So therefore why don't we just always ask? So
as we said there could be two possible explanations: one is the
person isn't around to ask, they made the thing forbidden to everyone
and then they walked away their thing, or the other is that
they really said I don't know I wasn't actually being that specific
you know I was trying to make a נדר Neder because that's
the point of course that David raises if the person isn't trying
to make a נדר Neder then you don't have פיו ולבו שוין.
Piv V'libo Shavin. I was trying to make it forbidden I heard
people use this language or I meant whatever this language means and
I had no particular meaning so then we would give it the
stricter meaning. Okay so that is the debate that is the issue
we had in the משנה Mishna and then a debate at the
end with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about
the difference in regions of גליל Galil and יהודה Yehuda what the
sort of standard meaning of a particular word חרם Cherem and תרומה
Teruma and so on might be. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
picks up in the גמרא Gemara at the bottom of י״ח עמוד
ב׳. Yud-Chet Amud Bet.
ודתנן ספק נזירות להקל V'hatnan Safek Nezirus L'hakel how can you say
סתם נדרים להחמיר Stam Nedarim L'hachmir if we say a ספק נזירות
Safek Nezirus is להקל L'hakel and a נזירות Nezirus is a type
of a נדר? Neder? So and we're assuming that it would probably
be a similar case where it's not clear what the word means.
Okay maybe other types of ספק Safek but then we would have
to explain why some ספקות Sfeikos we go לקולא L'kula and some
we go לחומרא. L'chumra. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי זעירא
Amar Rabbi Zeira so there's two ways of going here right the
one way of going or three ways of going: one way of
going would say that there's a difference between if there's a doubt
for other reasons as opposed to a question of the meaning of
the word; the second way of going would have been to say
that there is a difference between נזירות Nezirus and a נדר Neder
that maybe the specific characteristics of נזירות Nezirus hey welcome back nice
tan hey and thank you and thank you so much and the
third way is which is what the גמרא Gemara is going to
do. I find the first two ways more interesting but what the
גמרא Gemara is going to do is the third way which is
to say it's a מחלוקת תנאים. Machlokes Tannaim. Okay so let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי זעירא לא קשיא
הא רבי אליעזר הא רבנן. Amar Rabbi Zeira Lo Kashya Ha Rabbi
Eliezer Ha Rabbanan. It's the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
the רבנן. Rabbanan. דתניא Detanya we taught in a ברייתא Baraisa המקדיש
חייתו ובהמתו Hamakdish Chayato U'behemato
somebody basically says all of my חיה Chaya will be הקדש Hekdesh
or all of my בהמה Behema will be הקדש Hekdesh we're reading
the ו Vav here as or בהמתו. Behemato.
הקדיש את הכוי Hikdish Et Hakoi so the כוי Koi which is
this hybrid but it's a ספק. Safek. A כוי Koi is a
ספק Safek some say it might be a מין בפני עצמו Min
Bifne Atzmo it's some type of a hybrid what is it I
think between a deer and a I forget what it's a hybrid
between.
A type of ספק Safek I think that you can't clarify by
definition.
Well that's the מחלוקת Machlokes is it
a
ספק Safek right or is it a מין בפני עצמו? Min Bifne
Atzmo? What does it say there? Deer and something else? Yeah
okay I don't know anyway okay so it's
some type of a crossbreed all right so the גמרא Gemara says
רבי אליעזר אומר לא הקדיש את הכוי. Rabbi Eliezer Omer Lo Hikdish
Et Hakoi. So the חכמים Chachamim say it is sanctified we put
it by ספק Safek we'll put it into the חיה Chaya or
בהמה Behema category and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it is not
it's a ספק Safek it's not in the category. Now the
ר״ן Ran or תוספות Tosafos one of them basically points out that
actually רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds that a כוי Koi is a
מין בפני עצמו Min Bifne Atzmo so even if somebody said I
am being מקדיש Makdish all my חיות Chayos and all my בהמות
Behemos the כוי Koi wouldn't be קדוש Kadosh because it wouldn't be
because it's in neither category whereas the חכמים Chachamim say no no
if you said that it definitely would be קדוש Kadosh it's in
one of those two categories we just don't know which one. Okay
so therefore but if you said just חיה Chaya or just בהמה
Behema it's not קדוש. Kadosh. If you say חיה ובהמה Chaya U'behema
it would be קדוש. Kadosh. Anyway so what you see is here
there's a ספק Safek why don't we say ספק לחומרא? Safek L'chumra?
So the גמרא Gemara says that must be a debate right? I
mean רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is מקל Mekel but the חכמים Chachamim
are מקדיש Makdish are מחמיר Machmir so that's the debate of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים. Chachamim. Now again maybe רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer normally would say ספק לחומרא Safek L'chumra but maybe he's
just saying his idea by a כוי Koi because he thinks a
כוי Koi is neither one nor the other. But the גמרא Gemara
somehow is understanding that רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position is not unique
to כוי Koi it's not specific to his approach to כוי Koi
and he basically would say if you're מקדיש Makdish something and there's
a doubt which category it falls into whether it's included we say
it's outside of the category. And again הקדש Hekdesh is sort of
seen here similar to נדר Neder let's remember that the whole נדרים
Nedarim draws on the model of הקדש. Hekdesh. So therefore we think
that this debate what do you do if it's a ספק safek
is a debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and חכמים, Chachamim, and
that explains why our משנה mishna is מחמיר machmir by a נדר
neder and why the other משנה mishna is מיקל meikel by a
נזיר. nazir. Not a difference between a נדר neder and a נזיר,
nazir, but a general difference about whether we're מחמיר machmir or מיקל
meikel by ספק safek in these types of cases.
Yes. How can you have a חיה chaya that's not a domesticated
animal?
What does the ברייתא braita mean by that?
You can own deer. I mean, it doesn't... it's a מין min
that's not domesticated.
No, it's בדק הבית Bedek HaBayis anyway, can't bring it as a
קרבן. korban.
Oh, that's what you meant? As a קרבן? korban?
I didn't mean...
okay. As a קרבן korban fine, so who says it's a קרבן?
korban? It's a donation to בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayis. Just because the
מין min is not domesticated, right, some people have I don't know
snakes as pets or something, you know, so it doesn't mean that
this particular circumstance.
Yeah, and then they said there's different opinions but a female goat
and a male deer... oh sorry, a male goat and a female
deer.
Goat and a deer.
Okay. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So
מאן דאמר ממונא מעייל לספיקא, גופיה נמי מעייל. Man de'amar mamona maeil
lesfeka, gufeh nami maeil.
So according to the חכמים Chachamim that say that a ספק safek
about sanctifying your property is קדוש, kadosh, they would say the same
about making yourself into a נזיר. nazir. Now the גמרא Gemara is
signaling the fact that it recognizes that you could say there's a
difference. I'm more ready to make my property קדוש kadosh than to
make something about my own personal status, so maybe for making me
a נזיר nazir we would say ספק לקולא, safek lekula, but the
גמרא Gemara says no we're going to assume it's all the same.
So if they're מחמיר machmir by property, the חכמים, Chachamim, when you're
sanctifying your animals, they'd be מחמיר machmir by נזירות nezirus if it's
in a case of ספק. safek. מאן דאמר
ממונא לא מעייל לספיקא, Man de'amar mamona lo maeil lesfeka, but according
to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that even your property you're
not including in a case of doubt, so גופיה כל שכן דלא
מעייל לספיקא, gufeh kol shekein de'lo maeil lesfeka, how much more so
are you not including, would you not include your person in a
case of doubt and in the case of נזירות nezirus you would
not want to, if it's a ספק, safek, you would not want
to make yourself a נזיר. nazir. So therefore the debate we have
by sanctifying the animals would be a parallel debate by making yourself
a נזיר, nazir, although the גמרא Gemara signals the fact that it's
aware that you could have made a distinction and by the way
this is interesting because this actually could have been an answer. Right,
you have basically what's the problem? סתם נדרים להחמיר Stam nedarim lehachmir
and ספק נזירות להקל. safek nezirus lehakeil. So you could have said
that's the difference. A נדר neder is about objects, so if it's
just about the status of objects we'll take the stricter interpretation and
we'll make the objects אסור, asur, whereas נזירות nezirus is about me
and my status, so there we're going to be more lenient. We'll
say a person would be more reluctant to define themselves as a
נזיר nazir and therefore if there's any doubt we would say להקל.
lehakeil. So the גמרא Gemara signals that it's aware that you could
make a difference between objects and persons, which is exactly the difference
between a normal נדר neder and a normal נזיר nazir and that
would have exactly answered its question, but for some reason it ignores
that and wants to say it's a basic debate of תנאים. Tannaim.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's always not a problem, ספק לקולא,
safek lekula, whether it's a נדר neder or נזיר nazir or הקדש
hekdesh and the חכמים Chachamim say it's always strict, whether נדר, neder,
נזיר nazir or הקדש, hekdesh, it's always strict and making it a
debate of תנאים. Tannaim. The other thing that needs to be said
in addition to whether we're distinguishing between categories or whether we're making
it a debate is the idea that the גמרא Gemara is introducing
this issue about what's your intent or what you would want, right?
מעייל איניש נפשיה לספיקא? Maeil inish nafsheh lesfeka? מעייל ממוניה לספיקא? Maeil
mamonei lesfeka? Would you want to include yourself or your property in
cases of doubt? Now until it said that, I never in a
million years would have thought that this is an issue of what
you wanted. Meaning if it's about what you wanted, that's the second
discussion of פירושם להקל, peirusham lehakeil, right? But here you're not telling
us what you wanted. I would have thought that it's just a
legal question. How do we interpret statements that are of ambiguous meaning?
Right? Do we give them the stricter interpretation or the more lenient
interpretation? The more inclusive or more exclusive? So why it should matter
whether you would have wanted this or you would have wanted that?
You know, again, unless you're introducing the type of פירושם להקל peirusham
lehakeil as a speculating what that פירושן peirushan would have been. But
it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara is now making that idea
of what you would have wanted to do part of this conversation
of סתם להחמיר, stam lehachmir, סתם להקל. stam lehakeil.
Yes,
and ideologically it's part of a legal conversation. That is to say
if you have a legal text of authority for example, not a
statement but a text, and the text is ambiguous, one way of
clarifying is trying to go to the intent of the author.
That's a theory. Uh-huh.
So you're saying it's not because, not saying like in this particular
case we would say this is what you want, but we're basically
saying we'll choose to always interpret these statements more narrowly or more
broadly because as a general rule people when they're doing these types
of things are intending for either more narrowly or more broadly. Alright,
I hear that, that's a good point, that's a good point.
Yes, usually הקדש hekdesh has its own rules, right? I mean...
Right, well all of these you could say there's a difference between
נדר neder and נזיר nazir and הקדש. hekdesh. The גמרא Gemara is
throwing, that's my point, throwing them all in the same category. Okay,
so let's take a look. So it's made rather than distinguishing between
the categories, it is making it a מחלוקת תנאים. machlokes Tannaim. So
let's take a look. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי
Abaye responded to רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. במאי אוקימתא Bimai oquimta כסתם
נזירות להקל ke-stam nizarus lihakel
כרבי אליעזר. k-Rabbi Eliezer. So you're now saying that this approach of
ספק נזירות להקל safek nizarus lihakel is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who
says this also by a קוי koi that he's being מיקל meikil
and would say it by our משנה mishna that a נדר neder
would be מיקל meikil if there's a doubt. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa,
let's look at the end. ספק בכורות, safek bechoros, this is the
same משנה mishna that says ספק נזירות להקל, safek nizarus lihakel, says
ספק בכורות safek bechoros if there's a doubt about whether an animal
is a firstborn or not. A mother gave birth to twins, not
the human mother, a cow, let's say, and you don't know whether
the first one out was a boy or a girl. So you
don't know whether this boy baby is a בכור bechor or not,
because only if the boy was the first one out is it
a בכור. bechor. So what do you do with it? אחד בכור
אדם ואחד בכור בהמה, Echad bechor adam v-echad bechor behema, oh, it
could be a בכור אדם bechor adam about the פדיון הבן, pidyon
haben, בין טמא בין טהור bein tamei bein tahor
whether it's kosher or not kosher, because if it's a חמור chamor
you would still have to do the ritual of פדיון pidyon right
of
the- right the what do you call it? The- right the- and
breaking the neck, exactly, the- right, breaking the neck of the חמור,
chamor, excuse me, right. So המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה, hamotzi me-chaveiro alav
ha-rayah,
it's the חמור, chamor, excuse
me, thank you, you- excuse me, thank you, thank you, you give
the sheep or you break the neck of the חמור, chamor, thank
you all very much. Ah, you were paying attention, good. Okay, so
anyway, המוציא
מחבירו עליו הראיה. hamotzi me-chaveiro alav ha-rayah. If the כהן kohen wants
his five shekel for my kid, or the כהן kohen wants to
get my baby sheep or my baby calf, or if the כהן
kohen wants the baby sheep in exchange for the baby donkey, in
all those cases I would say to him, prove that it really
was a
בכור.
bechor. Since it's a כהן kohen anyway?
Well, fine, that's true, but the גמרא gemara imagines also you could
have all the כהנים kohanim in the world, you know, giving- yeah,
exactly, giving like what they call power of attorney to one particular
כהן. kohen. Anyway,
even if there was one particular כהן kohen that had standing and
was able to demand it, you would still say, you know, it's
a- in terms of who owns it, who has monetary rights, it's
a ספק safek whether I owe you this בכור, bechor, and therefore
go prove it to me, you can't prove it to me, I'm
not giving anything to you. That's in terms of חושן משפט, Choshen
Mishpat, of monetary rights. But now the question is, okay, I still
have this baby calf, if it is a בכור, bechor, I'm not
allowed to use it. A baby sheep, I'm not allowed to shear
it or whatever, I have to- you know, it has to be
brought as a קרבן. korban. So it's very nice that I wasn't
obligated to give it to the כהן, kohen, but
now it's
a ספק safek not in- right, not in חושן משפט, Choshen Mishpat,
now it's a ספק safek in יורה דעה, Yoreh Deah, right? It's
a ספק safek about how am I allowed to use this animal.
So that should be a biblical ספק, safek, a ספק דאורייתא safek
de-oraisa we would need to be strict. So the גמרא gemara says-
and it was practical differences for a person, right? The גמרא gemara
says ותני עלה v-sani alah
we taught a ברייתא braisa on this, שאסורין בגיזה ובעבודה, she-asurin be-giza
u-va-avoda,
you're not allowed to shear it or to work it. Okay, so
anyway, so what do you see? So presumably, this is the same
משנה mishna as ספק נזירות להקל, safek nizarus lihakel, which is a
presumably like a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer approach. And even though it
says ספק נזירות להקל, safek nizarus lihakel, we see that ספק בכורות
safek bechoros when it comes not to דיני ממונות dinei mammonos aspects
but to איסור והיתר issur v-heter aspects, we're being מחמיר. machmir. So
how is that consistent? Now, of course, the point is this had
nothing to do with saying that that משנה mishna was רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. It's just a straight question. Why do we say ספק
נזירות safek nizarus is מיקל meikil and why do we say ספק
בכורות safek bechoros is מחמיר, machmir, right? Okay, so that's a pretty
straightforward question, nothing really to do with רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. What's
the difference between בכור bechor and נזירות? nizarus? So the גמרא gemara
says, the גמרא gemara says, אמר ליה amar lei he said back
to him, אמי קמדמית קדושה באה מאליה לקדושה באה בידי אדם? ami
ka-medamis kedusha ba-a mei-e-leha l-kedusha ba-a b-yedei adam? Why are you comparing
a קדושה kedusha that comes by itself to a קדושה kedusha instilled
by a person? If a קדושה kedusha comes by itself, this בכור
bechor animal, this baby calf, is either בכור bechor or not, right?
It's nothing that I imparted that קדושה kedusha onto it. So, we
go to the normal principle that ספק דאורייתא לחומרא, safek de-oraisa l-chumra,
right? Since it might be a בכור, bechor, we have to be
strict, I don't want to transgress any prohibitions. Okay, whereas that's a
very different question when it's I'm instilling the קדושה kedusha into an
animal, or I'm making myself a נזיר, nazir, or making this loaf
of bread forbidden, where the question is, it starts by, what did
that language mean, what, you know, how to interpret my words. And
therefore if we adopt a principle that we'll interpret your words in
a narrower scope, in a narrower interpretation, we'll say that the thing
never became קדוש, kadosh, right? You understand the difference? In one case
it's a question of facts. What- what were the facts? Did this
animal, or was- was the baby calf born- boy calf born first
or was the baby girl calf born first? There's no way of
knowing based on one set of facts it's definitely אסור, assur, based
on the other it's definitely מותר, muttar, so it's a ספק דאורייתא
safek de-oraisa I have to be strict. The other is not really
a set of facts, we know what the facts are. I said,
I'm מקדיש maktish my חיה. chaya. I said a language that might
have meant נזירות nizarus or not. There's no question to the facts.
It's a question of law. It's a question of how do we
interpret what- what those words mean, right? And therefore if we- adopt
a legal principle that we're going to give those words a narrower
explanation meaning than the thing was never קדוש. kadosh. So there's no
way of comparing the normal rule of ספק דאורייתא לחומרא safek de'oraita
lechumra to the question of ספק safek you know about ספק נדרים
safek nedarim ספק נזירות. safek nezirus. All right, is that clear? ספק
דאורייתא לחומרא safek de'oraita lechumra is it's a question of the facts
and you have to be strict. ספק נזירות לקולא safek nezirus lekula
is the point about a legal question of what meaning do we
give your words, and רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position here identified with
רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer lenient will say we give your words the
narrowest meaning and not the broadest meaning. Okay, so that wasn't the
question. So the גמרא Gemara says fine. אלא אי קשיא הא קשיא.
ella ikasha hakasha. If I've got a question, here's my question.
Did you say that they're both... I mean, if you wanted to
make a parallel, they're
both looking for a
fact. In the one case you're looking for a fact that's actually...
Right, and the other is what you meant.
So you're looking for a fact. It's not a physical event, but
it's still a fact.
What's the fact?
Well, that's what they're looking for. No, they're looking for what was
in his mind.
what happened in that man's mind. Well, we're back to that, but
I don't... but that's not the point. The point is is that
if we know what... if he's going to tell us what happened
in his mind, maybe that's פירושן להקל. perushin lehakeil. The question is
that we don't... I don't think that the principle of סתם נדרים
להחמיר stam nedarim lechachmir is saying, I mean I guess you're right,
that could be what the גמרא Gemara means, or what the הוה
אמינא hava amina was, that סתם נדרים להחמיר stam nedarim lechachmir means
we have to guess what was within his mind and since we
don't know we have to adopt the stricter interpretation. You could say
that's what it means, right? And that would be why פירושן להקל,
perushin lehakeil, because if he tells us then we don't have to
guess. Right, I don't understand it that way, maybe because I'm a
little bit more of a formalist, and I understand it as no,
like, and this is the way actually the ר"ן Ran said. The
ר"ן Ran said 'I didn't have anything in my mind, I was
just using a language that I've heard people use.' So we need
a principle of what the words mean even if regardless of what
was in that person's mind or even if that person says 'I
wasn't thinking of one meaning or another meaning.' Okay? So it's not
just a question of what was in his mind, it's a question
of how we legally define what those words mean. Is that clear?
Okay. All right, but all right, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: 'Okay, אלא אי קשיא הא קשיא,' ella ikasha hakasha, if
I've got a question, here's my question. ספק משקין לטמא טמא לטמא
אחרים טהור דברי רבי מאיר.
safek mashkin letamei
tamei letamei acheirim tahor divrei Rabbi Meir. This is the end of
this משנה, Mishna, part of this משנה, Mishna, or at the beginning
of the משנה Mishna about ספק נזירות, safek nezirus, and it says
the following: ספק משקין לטמא טמא, safek mashkin letamei tamei, it lists
all different types of ספק, safek, right? So ספק בכור, safek bechor,
you get to keep it, but it's... you have to be מחמיר
machmir on how you treat the animal. ספק נזירות safek nezirus you're
מיקל. meikel. How about a completely different ספק? safek? I stuck my
hand
and, you know, my hand is טמא tamei and I stuck it
in and I might have touched some liquid and I might not
have touched that liquid, okay? What's the story? Is the liquid טמא
tamei or not? So now the reason we're talking about liquid is
as we'll see, because why don't you just apply normal principles of
ספק טומאה? safek tumah? Like ספק טומאה safek tumah we have a
principle: is it in a private domain, a public domain? There are
other principles to guide. Well, the one of the reasons here is
because liquid is basically a category where it might not be a
real biblical טומאה tumah by liquids at all. So that's part of
the reasons we're identifying liquid. So I stick my hand in, I
might have touched liquid or not. The הלכה halakha is,
so if it's about the thing itself becoming טמא, tamei, do I
treat the wine as טמא, tamei, let's say it was wine, then
I'd have to be strict, the wine is טמא. tamei.
לטמא letamei to become טמא tamei itself, טמא. tamei. לטמא אחרים, letamei
acheirim, now this wine is now going to touch other things, for
that הלכה halakha I'll say טהור, tahor, it's טהור. tahor. So I
split my vote. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
וכן היה רבי אליעזר אומר כדבריו. vechen haya Rabbi Eliezer omir kidvarav.
And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would agree with it. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, before we go ahead and figure out
how this is relevant to us, ומי סבירא ליה לרבי אליעזר לטמא
טמא? umi seira lei leRabbi Eliezer letamei tamei? Does רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer really hold that if there's a doubt whether the thing becomes
טמא, tamei, it's טמא, tamei, we have to be strict by liquids?
והתניא? vehatanya? We learned a ברייתא: Baraita: רבי אליעזר אומר אין טומאה
למשקין כל עיקר.
Rabbi Eliezer
omir ein tumah lemashkin kol ikar. That there is no biblical basis
for saying that liquids become טמא. tamei. תידע, teida, you should
know, שהעיד רבי יוסי בן יועזר איש צרידה על איל קמצא דכן
sheharei heid Rabbi Yose ben Yoezer ish Tzereda al ayyal kimtza dechan
or דכן, dechein, that a קמצא, kimtza, a certain type of a
locust, which the name of it was איל ayyal or I don't
know how to pronounce it, anyway, איל, eyal, איל, ayal, איל, ayal,
anyway, this type of a locust called an איל ayal was דכן.
dachen. דכן dachen is the Aramaic for טהור, tahor, meaning that it's
kosher, it can be eaten. ועל משקין בית מטבחיא דכן. veal mashkin
beit mitbachaya dachen. What? Right, exactly.
ועל משקין בית מטבחיא,
veal
mashkin beit mitbachaya, and the liquids literally in the slaughterhouse, but it
means in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash where they're always slaughtering animals,
דכן dachen is also טהור, tahor,
that you don't treat the blood that's coming out of all of
the animals and all the liquids going around there, you don't assume
that they will become טמא. tamei. And the reason is... is presumably
what's it based on is the principle that טומאת משקין tumas mashkin
is only rabbinic, and since the טומאה tuma of liquids is only
rabbinic, then in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash we're going to eliminate
it all together, we're going to go back to the biblical rule
because you do not want to have all this טמא tamei stuff,
all this stuff susceptible for טומאה, tuma, flying around in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so therefore we're going to just go back to
the biblical status. So the גמרא Gemara says, so you see, so
you see that he says it's טהור, tahor, so how could he
say here it's טמא? tamei? So, I mean now, obviously that's the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, this is not the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
but the difference is is that if he this shows us that
the whole status is rabbinic of liquids becoming טמא tamei and that's
why we don't apply it in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, then
also if there's a doubt we should be lenient, it should be
the principle that a ספק דרבנן לקולא, safek derabanan lekula, a doubt
about a rabbinic issue we're being lenient. So הניחא לשמואל דאמר דכן
מלטמא אחרים אבל טומאת עצמן יש בהן. Haniycha lishmuel de’amar dakhan milatamei
acherim aval tumat atzman yesh bahen. שמואל Shmuel says that what יוסי
בן יועזר Yosei ben Yoezer is saying is that these liquids in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash are pure in the sense that they
do not make other things טמא, tamei, okay, but they themselves do
become טמא. tamei. שפיר, shapir, it's good, that exactly actually maps onto
what our ruling is, meaning that there's an opinion that biblically speaking
liquids can become טמא tamei but they cannot make other things טמא.
tamei. Now that's perfect, because what did we say that if there's
a doubt if you touch the liquid that it is itself is
טמא tamei but it doesn't make other things טמא? tamei? So that's
perfect. ספק דאורייתא לחומרא ספק דרבנן לקולא. safek de’oraisa lechumra safek derabanan
lekula. And we say that biblically it becomes טמא tamei but it
doesn't make others, so there's a doubt, so for the biblical question
of does it become טמא tamei we'll say yes it's טמא, tamei,
we have to be strict. For the rabbinic question can it make
other things טמא tamei we'll be מיקל. makeil. Okay, that would work
perfectly. אלא, ela, but according to רב Rav דאמר דכן ממש, de’amar
dakhan mamash, that liquids biblically are טהור tahor completely, so מאי איכא
למימר? mai ika lemeimar? What can you say? Even though this is
only rabbinic, he's being strict. Okay fine, so that's an interesting question.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is strict about the טומאה, tuma, about the
liquids becoming טמא tamei even though it's only rabbinic. Now what does
that have to do with the price of tea in China or
the price of coffee at Zabar's, which is where our new coffee
is coming from? Anyway, okay, so it's not clear, right? Big deal,
big deal that we have רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who is being
strict about liquids becoming טמא tamei which is a rabbinic idea. What
does that tell us about why he can't hold that a language
you use for a נזיר nazir should be lenient? Okay, so the
ר״ן Ran says, I mean what does one have to do with
the other? First of all the difference the גמרא Gemara made, you
know קדושה באה מאליה קדושה ע״י אדם, kedusha ba’a me’eilya kedusha al
yedai adam, we made a whole big distinction about a question about
a question of facts which is measured one way and a question
of interpreting language which is measured another way. So the ר״ן Ran
says there's some loose comparison here. If he's willing to be so
strict that even in a rabbinic matter, although it is a question
of facts, but even if in a rabbinic matter of touching liquid
he's going to be strict, then in a biblical matter of making
yourself a נזיר nazir he should, you know, this guy's a מחמיר.
machmir. This is sort of like the way we think nowadays, but
it's not a precise way of thinking. Oh well, he's such a
מחמיר, machmir, I know this guy doesn't open bottle caps on שבת,
Shabbos, I can't believe, of course he's going to be מחמיר machmir
about something else, right? Who knows, maybe that has to do with
how he interprets ספקות sfekos and this has to do with a
completely different consideration. But this is the גמרא's Gemara idea. If he's
going to be מחמיר machmir about touching liquids which is דרבנן, derabanan,
how could he be מיקל makeil about ספק נזירות? safek nezirus? So
let's see what it answers. Not such a persuasive question for me
but let's see what it answers. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא,
ela, so the גמרא Gemara says you're right, let's drop the whole
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer approach. Anyway the whole רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
approach might have had to do more with his position about what
a כוי koy is than about anything else. Okay so let's just
forget the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer approach. We're back to our issue
which is our משנה mishna says that a נדר neder is, a
doubt we're מחמיר, machmir, and a נזיר nazir a doubt we're מיקל.
makeil. And let's see what we can do with this. אלא, ela,
here's how we're going to explain the difference between the משנה mishna
those two משניות. mishnayos. הא רבי יהודה הא רבי שמעון. Ha Rabbi
Yehuda Ha Rabbi Shimon. It's a debate of רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. And now here it
is specifically at least about a נזיר, nazir, so it's a lot
closer to home. דתניא, detanya, we taught a ברייתא braisa in נזיר:
Nazir: הריני נזיר אם יש בכרי זה, Haraini nazir im yeish bekeri
zeh, or בכרי bekeri I guess, מאה כור. me’ah kor. Okay, I
am a נזיר nazir if in this big pile of grain there's
a hundred, you know, liters of grain, okay? והלך ומצאו שנגנב או
שאבד, vehalach umetzau shenignav o she’avad, then you went to measure and
you found that somebody had stolen the grain. So
there's no way of knowing, there's no way of knowing. So you
have a doubt, you made your נזירות nezirus on a תנאי tnai
and you have absolutely no way that you will ever find out
whether that תנאי tnai was satisfied or not.
But there's no כרי keri there.
No, meaning, was there? Oh, yeah, exactly. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says So, what's the הלכה halacha, *halacha*? רבי יהודה אומר Rebbi Yehuda
omer, מתיר *Rabbi Yehuda omer matir*, you're not a נזיר nazir, *nazir*.
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon. אוסר *Rabbi Shimon oser*, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon.
*Rabbi Shimon* says you are a נזיר nazir, *nazir*. So basically here's
a question of ספק safek *safek* and it's a debate of רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*.
So that would be the opinion that says a ספק נזיר safek
nazir *safek nazir* is להקל le-hakeil *lehakeil* would be רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*. The position that says סתם נדרים stam nedarim *stam
nedarim* להחמיר lehachmir, *lehachmir*, again we're assuming נזיר nazir *nazir* and נדר
neder *neder* is the exact same. That would be רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon*, so the same way there's a debate between רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* about a ספק נזיר
safek nazir *safek nazir*, we assume it would be the same debate
about סתם נדרים stam nedarim *stam nedarim*. להחמיר le-hachmir. *Lehachmir* or להקל
le-hakeil. *lehakeil*. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says when there's a
doubt we're lenient and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says when there's a
doubt we're strict. Now again, I want to say that there's a
big difference between those two cases. There's a big difference between the
question of you don't know if a condition was met, okay, but
it was clear the person wanted to be a נזיר nazir *nazir*
and the question about how to interpret the language. How to interpret
the words, do you interpret them in their
meaning that's a binding meaning or non-binding meaning, okay? So that again
one could be just a question of a legal point of how
we're going to choose to interpret vague statements. The other could be
what do you do when you know it was clear what the
person wanted to do but you don't know if the conditions were
triggered. You could come out לחומרא *lechumra* in one place and לקולא
*lekula* in the other. There's no real logical reason to say that
they're the same question. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is putting them
together and therefore saying that those are making there's an opinion that's
always מיקל *meikel*, be מיקל *meikel* by נזיר nazir, *nazir*, מיקל *meikel*
by נדר neder *neder*. There's an opinion of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
that would be strict by נזיר nazir *nazir*, strict by נדר neder,
*neder*. Yes. You wanted to ask something?
I was so busy trying to ask you what I wanted to
ask you that the answer was what you just said please repeat
it.
Yes. I said the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sees these as the same
question. Whether we're strict or lenient in a question
when we have to decide what the words mean and whether we're
strict and lenient if we don't know if the condition was triggered.
And we assume that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* who is
lenient by the condition case in a נזיר nazir *nazir* would be
lenient by נדרים *nedarim* where there's a question about what the words
mean and רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* that's strict by the case of
the תנאי tnai. *tenai* by נזיר nazir? *nazir* would give the strict
meaning of words in cases of נדרים *nedarim*. Okay. So putting נזיר
nazir, *nazir* and נדר neder *neder* in the same category, we're putting
the question of a condition is met and the question of how
to interpret the words in the same category and we're assuming that
there's a מיקל *meikel* position and a מחמיר machmir. *machmir* position.
So when you're saying that you have a problem with the question
because it's two different cases, yeah, my question is so which would
you say which is which?
So I said you could go either way. I could see saying
as a legal principle I'll interpret the words in a non-binding way.
But if you definitely were trying to create a נזירות neziros. *neziros*
and there was a doubt if it was met and it's like
a ספק safek דאורייתא לחומרא *safek d'oraisa l'chumra*, right? So I could
say like that and I could say the reverse. As a legal
principle I'll assume that the words always have a binding meaning like
it's sort of like אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה *ein adam motzi
devarav levatala* type of an idea. I'll always give them a binding
meaning. Whereas if there's a doubt if a condition was met maybe
there'll be a principle
that נזירות neziros. *neziros* cannot take effect
unless it's clear. You know you could go either way. Alright, anyway
but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that it wants to see that
it's a debate about being a ספק safek, *safek* by נזירות nezirus
*neziros* and by נדר neder *neder* and it's all the same debate.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. ורמינהו דרבי יהודה
Yehudah אדרבי יהודה Yehudah *Veramino deRabbi Yehuda ad Rabbi Yehuda*. Now we're
going to show a contradiction of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
against himself. מי אמר רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda לא מעייל איניש נפשיה
לספיקא lo ma'ayil einish nafshiah lesfeika, *Mi amar Rabbi Yehuda lo ma'ali
inish nafshei l'sfeika*? Now again the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* again framing it
in this way of whether a person wants to or whatever. Since
when does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* really say? The רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* that's lenient here
by the case of the תנאי tnai *tenai* by the pile of
grain, right? And that you're not a נזיר nazir *nazir*. So we'll
say the logic behind it is you would not want to put
yourself into a space area of doubt. Meaning so you would only
want to be a נזיר nazir. *nazir*. Here's the logic behind it
that the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is spelling out again, more getting into
what's in your head than as a legal principle. You would only
want to be a נזיר nazir *nazir* if it was unequivocal and
therefore since it remains a doubt we would say you did not
want the condition to be binding. Okay. And that explains it and
similarly if you said a language that was a doubtful language you
would not want it to be binding if there were some doubt
in the language. Okay. So that's the logic. So does רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* really say that a person will not put
themselves into a place of doubt? ורמינהי *Veraminhi* and we'll ask on
this. רבי יהודה אומר סתם תרומה ביהודה Rebbi Yehuda omer stam terumah
b'Yehudah. *Rabbi Yehuda omer stam truma b'Yehuda* עד סוף המשנה *ad sof
hamishna*. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says that if you just
say the word תרומה trumah *truma* in יהודה Yehudah? *Yehuda* אסורה *asura*
it's forbidden because there it could mean תרומת הלשכה trumas halishka, *trumas
halishka* or תרומת הגורן terumat hagoren. *trumas hagoren* right ובגליל מותרת *ubagalil
muteres* and in the גליל Galil, *Galil* it's permissible שאין אנשי גליל
Galil מכירין את תרומת הלשכה terumat halishka. *she'ein anshei Galil makirin es
trumas halishka* because in the גליל Galil *Galil* when they say the
word תרומה trumah *truma* they never refer to תרומת הלשכה terumat halishka
*trumas halishka*. תרומת הלשכה terumat halishka *Trumas halishka* is a less common
phenomenon if they wanted to say תרומת הלשכה *trumas halishka* they'd say
תרומת הלשכה *trumas halishka*. The word תרומה trumah *truma* for them only
means the grain תרומה trumah *truma* and that is a non-binding word.
So טעמא דאין מכירין *ta'ama d'ein makirin* the reason it's not binding
is because cries, for them the word תרומה trumah only means the
תרומה terumah of the grain. הא
מכירין,
ha
makkirin, if they knew of two תרומות, trumos, they knew of the
תרומה terumah of the grain and they knew of the תרומה terumah
of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, of the תרומת הלשכה, so the
word could mean one, could mean the other, אסורין, assurin, it would
be forbidden, which basically means that if you read the משנה mishnah
you'll see the משנה mishnah we just read that רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda buys into the principle in our משנה mishnah סתם נדרים להחמיר,
stam nedarim lehachmir, right? Remember because רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda debates well,
yes סתם נדרים is להחמיר, le-hachmir but in certain regions where it
can only have the lenient meaning it'll be lenient. So תרומה in
the Galilee can only have the lenient meaning, it'll be lenient. But
the general rule is סתם נדרים להחמיר, stam nedarim lehachmir, right? So
how could you say that רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda. even though he's
lenient by a נזיר, nazir, it's not a general approach of leniency
in a case of doubt? He clearly is the author of the
משנה, mishnah, or he clearly agrees to the principle of the משנה
mishnah that סתם נדרים להחמיר, stam nedarim lehachmir, yes.
And the fact that it makes that distinction, yeah,
proves that in a case where if תרומה only means תרומת גורן,
trumas goren, then he's lenient, but if it could mean one or
the other he's מחמיר. machmir So he actually holds of סתם נדרים
להחמיר. stam nedarim lehachmir. So אמר רבא Amar Rava top of יוד
טית עמוד ב, yud tes amud bais, גבי קרי gabi keri קסבר
כל ספק חמור מודאי לא מעייל נפשיה לספיקא. kasavar kol safek chamur
mivadai lo ma'ail nafshiah l'sefeika.
Here's the difference. Again, I find this גמרא Gemara I just have
to say so frustrating, there were so many distinctions it could have
made between a נדר neder, and a נזיר, nazir, between language as
opposed to other areas of doubt. Here it makes it all about
whether you would have been wanted to have, what you would have
wanted to do in a case of doubt. Okay, so here it
says like this: By the pile of grain we'll say כל ספק
חמור
מודאי, kol safek chamur mivadai, it'll be worse to be a ספק
נזיר safek nazir than a ודאי נזיר. vadai nazir. Why is a
ספק נזיר safek nazir worse than a ודאי נזיר? vadai nazir? Because
a ודאי נזיר vadai nazir is over at the end of thirty
days. What does a ספק נזיר safek nazir. do at the end
of thirty days? Bring a קרבן? korban? Can't bring a קרבן, korban,
ספק חולין בעזרה. safek chulin ba'azarah. Can't bring a חטאת, chatas, right?
And whatever the קרבן korban he has to bring. So a ספק
נזיר safek nazir can't end his נזירות. nezirus, Now the ר"ן Ran
points
out that אם גילח על אחד משלושתן יצא, im gilach al achad
mishloshtan yatza, that if you bring like a שלמים shlamim or an
עולה olah which is one of the three קרבנות korbanos of a
נזיר nazir you could also end your נזירות. nezirus. Okay, but at
least anyway לכתחילה lechatchila it would be problematic, because you would not
be able to bring all your קרבנות. korbanos.
So easy to interpret it as ספיקא, sefeika, I want to be
a נזיר nazir, for thirty days or whatever it is, one of
these
ways where it says, wait, מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin he can never
end it?
Well, that's because the גמרא Gemara is understanding this, well let's take
a look. So let's see, exactly. So let's take a look. קסבר
כל ספק חמור מודאי, Kasavar kol safek chamur mivadai, being a ספק
safek? is worse than being a ודאי. vadai. לא מעייל נפשיה לספיקא,
Lo ma'ail nafshiah l'sefeika, you would not want to enter into that
doubtful category.
דאילו גבי נזיר ודאי D'ilu gabi nazir vadai מגלח ומייתי קרבן ונאכל,
megale'ach u'maiti korban v'ne'echal, and you can go ahead, he brings his
קרבן, korban, he shaves his head, and the קרבן korban is eaten.
אשפיקא לא מצי מגלח, A'sefeika lo matzi megale'ach, but by a ספק
safek. he can't. So what does it mean? It means the following.
רבי יהודה Yehudah would say, and then again, this gets us again
not to a legal principle but to just the principle of, well,
it's a ספק, safek? are we מחמיר machmir or מקיל meykeil by
a ספק? safek. We don't know, let's just play it safe type
of an approach. So there it's understanding that basically by a נדר
neder he says סתם נדרים להחמיר. stam nedarim lehachmir. We don't know
what it means, so we'll be strict, okay, we'll say it's אסור.
assur. Whereas by a נזיר, nazir we don't know what it means,
we don't know whether it takes effects or not by the case
about the תנאי. We're not going to be strict. Because if we're
going to be strict, he'll be totally stuck. He'll be a, meaning
we won't be strict and say he's a ודאי נזיר. vadai nazir.
We'll be strict and say he's a ספק נזיר. safek nazir? Okay,
and a ספק נזיר safek nazir is going to be in a
terrible situation. So we will say in that case he never would
have wanted it to have been binding משום ספק, mishum safek, because
to have been binding משום ספק mishum safek would have put him
in an impossible situation.
דאיכא דקאמר הכי ואיכא
דקאמר הכי.
D'ika d'ka'amar hachi
v'ika d'ka'amar hachi.
Exactly. So if there was any doubt whether it was binding, he
definitely would have wanted it to have not been binding. Whereas in
the case by a נדר, neder even if there's some doubt, he
would have wanted it to have been binding at least מספק, misafek,
which is now funny. Now it sounds like whether it's going to
be binding or not is not a decision, it's binding and when
it is binding it's ודאי. vadai. No, should we say that it's
binding מספק misafek or not? So by a נדר neder, we'll say
it's binding מספק, misafek, right? So let's say the guy said one
of these languages by a נדר neder and then he violated his
נדר, neder would we give him lashes? Maybe not. We're saying it's
binding מספק. misafek. We don't know, but we'll be strict. But by
a נזיר nazir we'll say he never would have wanted that type
of a possibility because of all the consequences and clearly it would
not be binding. Okay, so that's his way of resolving it. So
by the way, if we just take a step back and appreciate
what the גמרא Gemara now just said. Now we have an answer,
right? The whole thing started with a question that the משנה mishnah
said ספק נדרים להחמיר, safek nedarim lehachmir, we have a משנה mishnah
that says ספק נזירות להקל. safek nezirus lehakeil. But now we actually
have a better answer, forget רבי יהודה Yehudah? and רבי שמעון. A
נדר neder we're מחמיר on and a נזיר nazir, we're מקיל. meykeil.
You know why we're מקיל meykeil by a נזיר? nazir It's not
a debate of תנאים. tnai'im. Because a נזיר, nazir. who wants to
be a ספק safek, נזיר? nazir So that's why ספק נזירות safek
nezirus is להקל and ספק נדרים, safek nedarim, right, is להחמיר. Right,
remember, the גמרא Gemara is putting נדר neder and נזיר Nazir in
the same category and making it a debate of רבי יהודה Yehudah
and רבי שמעון. But now what it really is introduced is רבי
יהודה Yehudah contradicts himself. He's strict by a נדר, neder he's lenient
by a נזיר. Nazir Ah, because you're prepared to be
a, you know, to be a ספק נדר, safek neder, you're prepared
to live by, you're not prepared to live by a ספק נזירות.
safek nezirus. Okay, great, that's the answer. That's why סתם נדרים is
להחמיר and סתם נזירות stam nezirus is להקל. You don't need to
make it a debate of תנאים Tannaim anymore. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. אמליה רב הונא בר יהודה לרבא, Amlei Rav Huna
bar Yehuda le-Rava, so Rav Huna bar Yehuda said to Rava, אמר
הריני נזיר עולם מאי? Amar ha-reini nazir olam mai?
What about if he made this condition and he said if there's,
you know, if there's so much, you know, whatever, gallons or whatever
liters of grain, then I will be a נזיר Nazir. forever. Okay,
so then you could say there's no difference between being a ודאי
נזיר עולם vadai nazir olam and a ספק נזיר עולם. safek nazir
olam. Either way, right, he's never going to, his נזירות nezirus. won't
end. So in that case why don't we say, why don't we
say ספיקו לחומרא sfeiko le-chumra in that case, because there's no worse
being a ספק נזיר עולם? safek nazir olam? What, so maybe we
do, but since it didn't distinguish we assume it wouldn't matter. So
אמר ליה, Amar lei, נזיר עולם נמי ספיקו חמור מודאי? Nazir olam
nami sfeiko chamur mi-vadai? No, even in a נזיר עולם nazir olam
it's worse to be a doubtful נזיר עולם nazir olam than a
definite נזיר עולם. nazir olam. Why? דאילו ודאי, De-ilu vadai, a definite
נזיר, Nazir there's a הלכה, halacha. הכביד שערו מיקל בתער hikvid se'aro
meikel be-sa'ar that if
a, if the hair gets too heavy, he can actually trim it.
Like an option? Yeah, I guess. ומביא שלוש בהמות, u-meivi shalosh behemot,
you bring the בהמות behemot that you would normally bring to end
it, but you wouldn't end it, but somehow you would be allowed
לכתחילה. le-chatchila. It's a very bizarre הלכה. halacha I mean where do
you get this in the פסוקים? pesukim? But חז"ל Chazal understood that
if you have to live with this for your life, then you're
allowed by bringing the קרבנות korbanot it gives you a license to
trim your hair. Okay, to at least lighten it a little bit
if it gets to be too heavy. Okay, ואילו ספיקו לא. Ve-ilu
sfeiko lo. But not by a ספק. safek Why couldn't you do
it by a ספק? safek. Because it's a special הלכה
by a נזיר עולם. nazir olam. Well, actually I don't know why
you can't do it by a ספק. safek. Because if you, חולין
בעזרה? chulin ba-azarah?
Oh, right, thank you, it would be the חולין בעזרה chulin ba-azarah
point. Right, so if it would be a נזיר, Nazir. a normal
נזיר Nazir who was a ספק, safek. who just because he was
a ספק couldn't end his נזירות, nezirut. we wouldn't let the person
shave because we'd say you might not be, if you're a נזיר,
Nazir you're not a נזיר עולם. nazir olam. Only a נזיר עולם
nazir olam has the leniency to get a haircut. You're not a
נזיר עולם, nazir olam, you're a 30-day נזיר Nazir who doesn't know
whether you can end your, who's not able to end his נזירות.
nezirut Okay, but this case is you're either a ודאי נזיר עולם
vadai nazir olam or a ספק נזיר עולם. safek nazir olam. So
I think you're right, the reason a ספק נזיר Nazir can't do
it is because to do it you need to bring the
קרבנות. korbanot. Okay. So
basic question, yeah, let's go to
biblical models, right, that, you know, they were never able to do
it. Like who?
שמע, Shema, the next question in the גמרא. Gemara אמר הריני נזיר
שמשון מאי? Amar ha-reini nazir Shimshon mai? Okay, so there's this category
called נזיר שמשון, nazir Shimshon, right, because שמשון Shimshon never cut his
hair. So anyway, so what's נזיר שמשון? nazir Shimshon? נזיר שמשון nazir
Shimshon is very bizarre. On the one hand, you're allowed to become
טמא למתים. tamei le-meitim. If somebody is this concept of נזיר שמשון
nazir Shimshon because שמשון Shimshon did kill people. Right, so it's quite
amazing, like the תורה Torah doesn't have this category, right, yeah, but
we see it in תנ"ך. Tanach. שמשון Shimshon was a נזיר Nazir,
and we see that a, he could never cut his hair, and
b, that he could become טמא tamei to dead people. So therefore
from there we learn out that there's this concept called נזיר שמשון
nazir Shimshon where you could become טמא tamei to dead people but
you can never cut your hair even if you're a נזיר, Nazir
whatever, right, even if you're a נזיר עולם. nazir olam. So if
somebody said, made this condition, and if this condition is met I'll
be a נזיר שמשון, nazir Shimshon, there's no worse being a ודאי
נזיר שמשון vadai nazir Shimshon or a ספק נזיר שמשון. safek nazir
Shimshon. Either way, you'll never be able to do anything to lighten
your hair and your נזירות. nezirut So so that case why shouldn't
we say the תנאי is binding? אמר ליה נזיר שמשון לא תניא.
Amar lei nazir Shimshon lo tanya. Give me a break, we're not,
we're, you know, we're not addressing cases of נזיר שמשון. nazir Shimshon.
Maybe if somebody said נזיר שמשון, nazir Shimshon, maybe you're right, maybe
it would be binding. But since when is the משנה Mishnah going
to be talking about a case of a נזיר שמשון? nazir Shimshon?
So אמר ליה והאמר
אביי בר אבין תניא נזיר שמשון.
Amar lei ve-ha-amar
Abbaye bar Avin tanya nazir Shimshon. So Abbaye bar Avin said actually
we have a ברייתא braita that actually says this exact scenario of
if there's a hundred כור kor then I'll be a נזיר שמשון.
nazir Shimshon. Has a ברייתא braita that gives the scenario with נזיר
שמשון nazir Shimshon and still has רבי יהודה Yehudah saying it's not
binding, and according to you it should be binding because there's nothing
worse about being a doubtful נזיר than a definite נזיר. אמר ליה
אי תניא תניא. Amar lei i tanya tanya. Okay, if you got
a ברייתא, braisa, you got a ברייתא, braisa, but you know, I
still don't think it makes sense, which basically means like either it's
a מחלוקת תנאים machlokes Tannaim or about whether we would say it,
or I never heard of that ברייתא, braita, but fine, whatever, you
got a ברייתא, braisa, but I'm really not persuaded. All right, anyway,
רב אשי אמר. Rav Ashi amar. Okay, so now what do we
have? We basically have an answer that is we have a debate
by נזיר whether it's binding in a case of ספק. Okay, so
the משנה Mishnah that says ספק נזירות להקל safek nezirus le-hakeil is
certainly רבי יהודה who says it's not binding in a case of
ספק. We wanted but we can't say that that's the same issue
of the debate of נזירות *Nezirus* by נדר *Neder* because the same
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* that says סתם נדרים להחמיר stam nedarim lehachmir,
*Stam Nedarim le-hachmir* says סתם נזירות להחמיר stam nezirut lehachmir. *Stam Nezirut
le-hachmir*. So in the end what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has wound
up saying is not that it's a debate of תנאים Tannaim *Tannaim*
but it's a difference between נדר *Neder* and a נזיר *Nazir*. By
a נדר *Neder* you're okay with it being אסור מספק misfek, *assur
mi-safek*. By a נזיר *Nazir* you would never want to become a
נזיר מספק misfek. *Nazir mi-safek* and therefore we'll always interpret it in
the more lenient way. Yes.
Just practically the TLDR behind that statement? What do...
yeah you can go to a חכם *chacham* and get a היתר
*heter* right?
It's interesting I'm still having difficulty with the concept of why somebody
would make such a severe statement and base it on chance. In
other words
what's their real intention?
Well you're right meaning it might sort of be the opposite like
we're
arguing and we're saying I am telling you there was so much
grain in there there must have been a hundred כור kor *kor*
of grain. You're crazy there wasn't more than fifty כור *kor* of
grain in there. If there weren't a hundred כור *kor* of grain
in there then I'll be a נזיר *Nazir*. So it could be
something like that it's more
like it's less wanting to be a נזיר *Nazir* and more wanting
to win an argument.
I was taking it like this guy seriously wants...
Right. I don't know who knows?
But if they really want
it
they would not want to take the chance.
Exactly.
Yeah maybe it's just
I don't know.
You're right I mean yeah.
So do you use it like context at all if you're just
saying דברים של גוזמא *dvarim shel guzma*?
Well that's an interesting question. That might be a פיו ולבו שוין
*pi ve-libo shavin* type of thing and maybe we would. Okay and
we'll actually get to that נדרי טועה *Nidrei tohu* and נדרי הבאי
*Nidrei hava* and whatever. So we'll get to things like that actually
where exactly that you're making it as an exaggeration. Okay so let's
take a look. All right so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
It says like this: רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* okay דתניא דתניא *De-tanya
De-tanya* רב אשי אמר *Rav Ashi amar* היא רבי יהודה משום רבי
טרפון Rebbi Tarfon היא *hi Rabbi Yehuda mishum Rabbi Tarfon hi*. That
is the position is that of that a נזיר *Nazir* is making
that by ספק נזירות *sfek Nezirut* will go לקולא *le-kula* is not
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*'s own position. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* is סתם
נדרים להחמיר stam nedarim lehachmir, *stam Nedarim le-hachmir* and he would actually
say סתם נזירות להחמיר *stam Nezirut le-hachmir*. So what's this position by
that grain that we're מקל *meikel*? That's רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* saying
it in the name of רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon*. דתניא דתניא *De-tanya
De-tanya* רבי יהודה משום רבי טרפון אומר אין אחד מהם נזיר לפי
שלא ניתנה נזירות אלא ela להפלאה *Rabbi Yehuda mishum Rabbi Tarfon omer
ein echad me-hem Nazir lefi she-lo nittena nezirut ela le-hafla'ah*. That basically
you have a case which was two people were going down the
road. חיים *Chaim* and I were walking down the road and we
saw somebody in the distance. I said חיים *Chaim* that looks like
Michael there and חיים *Chaim* said you're crazy that isn't Michael. So
I say I'll be a נזיר *Nazir* if that is Michael and
חיים *Chaim* says I'll be a נזיר *Nazir* if that isn't Michael.
Okay? So one of us has got to be a נזיר *Nazir*
right? There's only two sets of possibilities in the world: A and
not A. Okay? So the הלכה *halacha* is so says רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* in the name of רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* neither of
us is a נזיר *Nazir* whether whoever it is okay why? שלא
ניתנה נזירות אלא להפלאה *she-lo nittena nezirut ela le-hafla'ah*. It says: איש
או אשה כי יפלא לנדור נדר נזיר *Ish o isha ki yafli
lindor neder nazir* איש או אשה כי יפלא לנדור נדר נזיר להזיר
לה׳ *Ish o isha ki yafli lindor neder nazir lehazzir la-Hashem*. Okay
and what does יפלא *yafli* mean? יפלא *yafli* means like to enunciate
to articulate. It actually becomes a word as I've told you at
the beginning הפלאה *hafla'ah* means sort of things that are created through
speech acts: נדר *Neder* שבועה *shvuah* נזירות *nezirut* הקדש *hekdesh* even is
הפלאה *hafla'ah*. Anyway
but here it's understood to mean that it is
unambiguous right articulated and unambiguous and therefore precise. So therefore if there's
any doubt at the time it was made even though
like from God's eye there was no doubt it either was or
wasn't Michael it wasn't even about something in the future it was
about something in the present like the pile of grain just we
didn't know. If it wasn't clear at the moment it was accepted
it's not binding. In a way maybe that's reflecting David's point if
you gotta be serious about this so if there's any doubt it's
not binding. And this by the way is the legal principle. Right?
So there's a legal principle of ספק נזירות להקל *safek nezirut le-hakel*.
It's not whether you want it it's not what was in your
mind it's not whatever.
Exactly exactly. It's the principle that נזירות *nezirut* does not take effect
unless it's black and white.
And מסכת נדרים *Masechet Nedarim* is probably a lot shorter right?
Yeah you wish. אי הכי ei hachi *Ei hachi* says the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* oh so that's why. So basically רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
himself could be מחמיר *machmir* and say סתם נדרים להחמיר stam nedarim
lehachmir. *stam Nedarim le-hachmir*. Now what is the גמרא *Gemara* saying? Is
the גמרא *Gemara* saying סתם נדרים להחמיר stam nedarim lehachmir. *stam Nedarim
le-hachmir* but סתם נזירות להקל *stam Nezirut le-hakel* because נזירות *nezirut* has
a special requirement of כי יפלא *ki yafli*? It doesn't exactly sound
like that. It sounds like there's two opinions out there. There's an
opinion that ספק לקולא *safek le-kula* כי יפלא *ki yafli*. That applies
by נזיר *Nazir*. That's in the name of רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon*
not רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* himself רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* in the
name of רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon*. And maybe that applies to נדר
*Neder* as well and maybe by נדר *Neder* we would also be
מקל *meikel* based on that principle. And then there's a position that
rejects it rejects it by נדר *Neder* and maybe rejects it by
נזיר *Nazir*. So rather than making a נדר *Neder*-נזיר *Nazir* distinction which
is the most obvious... and the one the גמרא seemed to have
made before, here it again seems to be falling back into this
debate of תנאים Tannaim, positions. So let's read this. Okay, so the
גמרא says like this. אינו לפי שלא תהא נזירות אלא במופלא. eino
lefi shelo tehei nezirut ela bemufla. אי הכי says the גמרא מאי
איריא שנגנב או שנאבד? mai irya shenignav o shena'avad? אלא why does
it say that you went and there was not you couldn't measure
the grain? Even if you could measure the grain, since you didn't
know at the time, remember you made a I'll be a נזיר
if there's so much grain, since you didn't know at the time,
it should not be binding. It doesn't matter. I thought it was
Michael, it turned out to be Michael when I made that thing,
but I'm not a נזיר because I didn't know at the time.
Okay, even if you thought you knew, you're right. What do you
mean I didn't know? I did know. But nevertheless, it wasn't somehow
clear to everyone. Okay, that's a good point. It's not enough that
I say I knew. I told you it was Michael, I saw
him. No, it wasn't clear to everyone and therefore it's not a
נזירות. Okay, so that's true even if you go ahead and you
measure the grain, you shouldn't be a נזיר. So אי הכי מאי
איריא שנגנב או שנאבד ei hachi mai irya shenignav o shena'avad why
does it say it was stolen or lost? אלא דהא כולה כדרבי
שמעון. ela deha kula k'Rebbi Shimon.
You're right. According to רבי יהודה that says you're not a נזיר
even if you measured it and saw there was a hundred כור
you wouldn't be a נזיר. But it's telling you a חידוש chiddush
for רבי שמעון דאף על גב דנגנב או שאבד de'af al gav
denignav o she'avad even though it's not around and therefore א alef
it wasn't clear at the time, ב bet you have no way
now of knowing whether the condition was met, nevertheless קסבר מעייל איניש
נפשיה לספיקא kasavar ma'ayil einish nafshiah lesfeika that you are still considered
a נזיר out of doubt, you are willing to become a נזיר
out of doubt. Okay, so it's to tell you the strict position
but really it was the bigger חידוש chiddush would have been the
more lenient position. So bottom line, what's the גמרא saying? Is it
saying סתם נדרים להחמיר סתם נזירות להקל? stam nedarim lehachmir stam nezirut
lehakel? You could say it's a נדר נזיר distinction and for one
of two reasons. Either because לא מעייל איניש נפשיה לספיקא, nobody wants
to be a נזיר מספק, but some thing could be a נדר
מספק. Or because כי אתפי, ki atfei, it's a special נזירות idea.
Or what the גמרא seems to be saying at the end is
it seems to be not saying נזירות is different, but again going
back to this debate of תנאים, Tannaim there's some תנאים that require
that everything be black and white, unambiguous, and if it's not, it's
not binding. They say it by נזיר, that's רבי טרפון and maybe
presumably they would say it by נדר as well. And then there
are others that don't say that and say that if there's a
doubt, it's going to be it will be strict. That's סתם נדרים
להחמיר, maybe we would also say סתם נזירות להחמיר. Again, it seems
much easier to say נזיר נדר distinction than to put them all
in the same category, but that seems to be the approach that
the גמרא is doing. And I again want to repeat the point
that there's a logically you could easily make a difference between the
question of how do you interpret a statement and language and a
question about when a condition is whether a condition is met or
not. Those also very much could be different types of issues. Okay,
so let's now take a look, let's just finish up to the
end of the דף. daf. We'll hold off any questions until we
finish the דף. daf. רבי יהודה אומר סתם תרומה stam terumah ביהודה.
Okay, so this is going to be pretty straightforward. I mean it
says that רבי יהודה says that סתם תרומה in יהודה is going
to be strict because it could mean תרומת הלשכה. In the גליל,
Galil it only can mean תרומה of grain and therefore we're going
to be lenient. So the גמרא says רבי יהודה אומר, so the
גמרא says הא מכירים, ha'makirim, if in the גליל they were aware
of תרומת הלשכה so there would be an equal doubt, אסורין, asurin,
it'd be forbidden because רבי יהודה agrees that סתם נדרים להחמיר, right,
we've made that point before. So the גמרא says אלמא ספק לחומרא
alma safek lechumra if there's a doubt we're strict, סתם נדרים להחמיר.
אימא סיפא eima seifa let's look at the end. סתם חרמים ביהודה
מותרין ובגליל אסורין. stam charamim b'Yehudah mutarin uv'Galil asurin.
This is still רבי יהודה speaking. The word חרם cherem in Judea
it's permissible and in the גליל it's forbidden. שאין אנשי הגליל מכירים
את חרמי כהנים. she'ein anshei haGalil makirim et charmei kohanim. In the
גליל the word חרם cherem cannot mean חרמי כהנים, charmei kohanim, it
only means חרם cherem to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash so it's
forbidden. Whereas in יהודה the word חרם cherem can mean חרמי כהנים
charmei kohanim and therefore and חרמי כהנים charmei kohanim is not a
term for a נדר and therefore we are going to be what
are we going to say in יהודה? We're going to be lenient
because the word could mean חרמי כהנים, charmei kohanim, but here's the
problem. Who cares if it could mean חרמי כהנים? charmei kohanim? It
also could mean חרם cherem to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So
just because in יהודה it might have the lenient meaning but it
also might have the strict meaning, so why are we being lenient
in יהודה? Is that question clear? Right? When we dealt with תרומה
we said in יהודה תרומה could mean either the strict meaning or
the lenient meaning, תרומת הלשכה or תרומת הגורן. So we give it
the strict, סתם נדרים להחמיר.
Now he's saying when you use the word חרם cherem in יהודה
it could have the strict meaning, it could have the lenient meaning,
the lenient meaning is חרמי כהנים, charmei kohanim, and we're going to
be lenient. Why are we going to be lenient? If it could
have either meaning we should be strict. Okay, so the גמרא says
אלמא ספק לקולא alma safek lekula
looks like in יהודה if it could mean חרם cherem could mean
both possibilities we'll be lenient. Why are we lenient? אמר אביי סיפא
רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק היא. amar Abaye seifa Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Tzadok
hee. You're right. The last line is not רבי יהודה. The last
line is a position of רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi
Tzadok that actually says ספק. יהודה *Yehuda* it could mean תרומה *teruma*
could mean תרומת הלשכה *terumat halishka*. רבי
אלעזר ברבי צדוק אומר *Rabbi Elazar be-Rebbi Tzadok omer*: סתם חרמים בגליל
אסורים *stam charamim ba-Galil assurim*. It’s רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק *Rabbi Elazar
be-Rebbi Tzadok* who says that in גליל *Galil* חרם *cherem* is
אסור *assur*, but in יהודה *Yehuda* חרם *cherem* would be permitted, presumably
because it could mean both things and actually רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק
*Rabbi Elazar be-Rebbi Tzadok* would be saying סתם נדרים להקל *stam nedarim
lehakel*. So of course the irony is we went through this whole
סוגיא *sugya* before trying to figure out סתם נזירות להקל *stam nezirut
lehakel* who it’s going like, and the גמרא *Gemara* in the end
seems to point that, hey, look, there’s a רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק
*Rabbi Elazar be-Rebbi Tzadok* that seems to say, implicit in his statement
is סתם נדרים להקל *stam nedarim lehakel*. So we just could have
said it was all going according to him, which sort of the
ר"ן *Ran* says. Of course the other possibility is if you could
say, no, in general he agrees סתם חרמים להחמיר *stam charamim lehachmir*,
סתם נדרים להחמיר *stam nedarim lehachmir*, but maybe he just says that
in יהודה *Yehuda* the word חרם *cherem* is not a ספק *safek*.
The word חרם *cherem* only means חרמי כהנים *charmei kohanim* in יהודה
*Yehuda*, right? You could have made the argument, right, that in יהודה
*Yehuda* it’s not like it also means חרמי כהנים *charmei kohanim* and
we’re מיקל *meikel*. You could have said in יהודה *Yehuda* it’s so
prevalent to do חרמי כהנים *charmei kohanim* that if you wanted to
say חרמי מקדש *charmei mikdash* you’d say חרמי מקדש *charmei mikdash*, but
חרם *cherem* by itself only means חרמי כהנים *charmei kohanim*. But the
גמרא *Gemara* doesn’t say that. The גמרא *Gemara* seems to say that
the רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק *Rabbi Elazar be-Rebbi Tzadok* is being lenient
in יהודה *Yehuda* because he would say סתם נדרים להקל *stam nedarim
lehakel*. So after going through that whole long other discussion, actually we
find that there’s an opinion that actually says, right, that סתם נדרים
*stam nedarim* is להקל *lehakel*.
Okay. But how can he say that's דאורייתא *doraisa*?
What do you mean? That it's דאורייתא *doraisa* same like by נזיר
*nazir*, like what we introduced by the idea by נזיר *nazir*, right,
that להפלי *lehafli* and that principle could apply to נדרים *nedarim* as
well.
So that was what I was going to ask earlier
because how do we know to apply נדרים *nedarim* to נזר *nezer*?
Well, like we learned before, נדרים *nedarim* נזר *nezer*. Exactly.
I just wanted to know if that’s
the גזירה שוה *gezeira shava*. Yeah, that presumably is why.
Okay.